First dance. First love. The time of your life.
Dirty Dancing is a drama, music, romance film directed by Emile Ardolino.
Expecting the usual tedium that accompanies a summer in the Catskills with her family, 17-year-old Frances 'Baby' Houseman is
surprised to find herself stepping into the shoes of a professional hoofer—and unexpectedly falling in love.
Frances "Baby" Houseman, played by Jennifer Grey.
Johnny Castle, played by Patrick Swayze.
Penny Johnson, played by Cynthia Rhodes.
Billy Kostecki, played by Neal Jones.
Dr. Jake Houseman, played by Jerry Orbach.
Marjorie Houseman, played by Kelly Bishop.
Dirty Dancing is a 1987 American romantic drama dance film written by Eleanor
Bergstein, produced by Linda Gottlieb, and directed by Emile Ardolino.
Starring Patrick Swayze and Jennifer Grey, it tells the story of Frances "Baby" Houseman (Grey), a young woman who falls in
love with dance instructor Johnny Castle (Swayze)  while vacationing at a resort in the 1963 Borscht Belt.
The film was based on screenwriter Bergstein's own childhood.
She originally wrote a screenplay for the Michael Douglas 1980 film It's My Turn, but she
ultimately ended up conceiving a story for a film which became Dirty Dancing.
She finished the script in 1985, but management changes at
Metro-Goldwyn-Mayer put the film in development hell.
The production company was changed to Vestron Pictures with Emile
Ardolino as director and Linda Gottlieb as producer.
Filming took place in Lake Lure, North Carolina, and Mountain Lake, Virginia, with the
film's score composed by John Morris and dance choreography by Kenny Ortega.
Dirty Dancing premiered at the Cannes Film Festival on May 12, 1987 and was released on August 21 in the United States,
earning over $214 million worldwide—$64 million in the US and Canada and $150 million in other territories.
It earned positive reviews from critics, who particularly praised the performances of Grey and Swayze, and its
soundtrack, created by Jimmy Ienner, generated two multi-platinum albums, and multiple singles.
"(I've Had) The Time of My Life", performed by Bill Medley and Jennifer Warnes, won the Academy Award for Best Original Song, the
Golden Globe Award for Best Original Song, and the Grammy Award for Best Pop Performance by a Duo or Group with Vocals.
In 2024, the film was selected for preservation in the United States National Film Registry by the
Library of Congress as being "culturally, historically, or aesthetically significant".
The film's popularity successfully launched its titular franchise, including a 1988 television series, multiple reality competition shows, a 2004 prequel titled Dirty Dancing: Havana Nights, a stage production
which has had sellout performances in multiple countries, a made-for-television musical adaptation in 2017, and an untitled sequel scheduled to be released in 2025 with Grey reprising her role.
The film explores themes of hotel, daughter, dancing, secret love, robbery.
The tone is lighthearted and emotional.